<xml><article id="32040923" name="Circular SECEX 016_2023_6" idOficio="9587155" pubName="DO1" artType="Circular" pubDate="11/05/2023" artClass="00019:00029:00000:00000:00000:00000:00000:00000:00000:00000:00016:00000" artCategory="Ministério do Desenvolvimento, Indústria, Comércio e Serviços/Secretaria de Comércio Exterior" artSize="24" artNotes="Ok&#xA;texto em portugues, algumas citações em lingua estrangeira." numberPage="167" pdfPage="http://pesquisa.in.gov.br/imprensa/jsp/visualiza/index.jsp?data=11/05/2023&amp;jornal=515&amp;pagina=167" editionNumber="89" highlightType="" highlightPriority="" highlight="" highlightimage="" highlightimagename="" idMateria="20587807">
  <body>
    <Identifica />
    <Data><![CDATA[]]></Data>
    <Ementa />
    <Titulo />
    <SubTitulo />
    <Texto><![CDATA[<p>143. Em seguida, as peticionárias afirmaram que outra particularidade seria o controle que o Partido exerceria, direta ou indiretamente, sobre os bancos, o que facilitaria a intervenção do Estado na economia. Nesse sentido, apresentou memorando específico sobre a China, emitido pelo Departamento de Comércio dos Estados Unidos, no qual teria sido indicada a forma de organização do sistema financeiro chinês, que incluiria:</p><p>(1) five large commercial banks ("Big Five") that are majority state-owned, operate large branch networks on a nationwide basis, and accounted for approximately 40% of bank assets in 2015;</p><p>(2) 12 joint-stock commercial banks (JSBs) that operate with generally lower levels of direct government ownership, operate on a nationwide basis, and accounted for approximately 19% of bank assets in 2015;</p><p>(3) approximately 145 city commercial banks and credit unions that generally remain under local government control, serve local markets, and accounted for approximately 14% of bank assets in 2015;</p><p>(4) three wholly state-owned policy banks that focus on infrastructure, agriculture and rural development, and foreign trade, respectively, and accounted for approximately 10% of bank assets in 2015;856 and</p><p>(5) foreign-owned banks and bank branches that accounted for 2% of bank assets in 2015, unchanged from 2006".</p><p>144. As peticionárias concluíram que a maior parte dos ativos do sistema financeiro chinês se concentra no Estado. Assim, a alocação de recursos ocorre considerando as políticas e metas governamentais estabelecidas.</p><p>145. No que diz respeito ao setor de energia elétrica, as peticionárias alegaram, com base em documento elaborado por Fredrich Kahrl, Jim Williams e Ding Jianhua no âmbito do fórum "China Environment Forum", que a motivação para a manutenção do controle estatal repousaria na concentração do poder de decisão na National Development and Reform Commission ("NDRC"), que minimizaria a influência da State Electricity Regulatory Commission ("SERC"), criada com objetivo de se tornar uma agência reguladora do setor:</p><p>Efforts at independent regulation of the electricity sector in China have run into two primary roadblocks. First, SERC does not have the powers or authority to be an effective regulator. SERC was never given approval, planning, or ratemaking powers. Key decision-making powers for the electricity sector are instead concentrated in the National Development and Reform Commission (NDRC), China's chief planning agency. National state-owned enterprises in China's electricity sector, and in particular the State Grid Corporation, are often more powerful than SERC, which, because China lacks an independent judiciary, leaves SERC with few direct options for enforcing the rules.</p><p>146. As peticionárias acrescentaram a esse respeito que, segundo Edward A. Cunningham em seu artigo intitulado "The State and the Firm: China's Energy Governance in Context", duas das formas mais diretas de intervenção do governo chinês no setor de fornecimento de energia elétrica seriam por intermédio da (i) indicação de executivos via SASAC (State-owned Assets Supervision and Administration Commission) e da (ii) aprovação de projetos de fornecimento de energia elétrica de médio e longo porte pela NDRC.</p><p>147. Adentrando os elementos que indicariam especificamente que o setor produtivo de cabos de fibra óptica não operaria em condições de economia de mercado, as peticionárias abordaram os aspectos principais: (i) das políticas sobre produtos de alta tecnologia; (ii) da Broadband China Strategy; (iii) dos Planos Quinquenais; e (iv) do plano Made in China 2025.</p><p>148. As peticionárias apontaram que a China adotou políticas, guias e programas para promover a pesquisa e o desenvolvimento do setor de alta tecnologia. Para tanto o governo chinês elaborou catálogos com a definição de produtos de alta tecnologia, como por exemplo o China´s High Technology Export Products, que faz menção a produtos que "can enjoy the state's preferential policies for the export of high-tech products in accordance with the relevant regulations of the country".</p><p>149. Outro catálogo citado foi o Foreign Investment Promotion High and New Technology Product Catalogue que orienta a política industrial para investidores estrangeiros e indica quais os setores industriais são incentivados a receber investimento estrangeiro. Dentre os setores mencionados, foi possível identificar setores relacionados ao produto objeto da presente investigação:</p><p>77. Production of optical fibers and their products: optical fiber bundles for image transmission and laser optical fibers for medical treatment, supersecond-generation and third-generation microchannel plates, optical fiber panels, image inverters, and glass fiber cones.</p><p>(...)</p><p>266. Manufacturing of time division multiplexing equipment (TDM) with rate of 100 Gbps or more, dense wavelength division multiplexing equipment (DWDM), broadband passive network equipment (including EPON, GPON, WDM-PON, etc.), next-generation DSL chips and equipment, optical crossconnect (OXC) equipment, automatically switched optical network (ASON) equipment, and transmission equipment for optical fiber communication at more than 40 Gbps SDH.</p><p>150. O documento Catalogue of Major Industries, Products and Technologies Encouraged for Development in China também menciona o setor produtivo atinente a cabos de fibra óptica:</p><p>13. Posts and Telecommunications - Digital synchronization series' optical fiber communications systems and equipment, at 622 Mb/s or faster.</p><p>151. A petição forneceu o Catalogue for the Guidance of Industrial Structure Adjustment, que fez alusão a setores relacionados a cabos de fibra óptica, a saber:</p><p>28. Information Industry</p><p>1. Construction of 2.5GB/s and above optical synchronous transmission system;</p><p>28. Manufacturing of new (non-dispersive) single-mode optical fiber and optical fiber preform.</p><p>152. As peticionárias mencionaram a Law of the People's Republic of China on Progress of Science and Technology, que destaca as ações de fomento ao desenvolvimento da área de ciência e tecnologia, na qual se insere o setor produtivo de cabos de fibra óptica. Dentre as provisões constantes da referida lei, destacam-se:</p><p>An entity that is engaged in the following activities shall enjoy preferential tax policies in accordance with the relevant regulations of the State: engaging in other activities for scientific research and technological development, or application of scientific and technological advances as provided for in laws and relevant State regulations.</p><p>(...)</p><p>State shall encourage financial institutions to carry out the business of hypothecation of intellectual property rights, encourage and give guidance to such institutions in supporting the application of scientific and technological advances and the development of high and new technology industries by granting loans, etc., and encourage insurance agencies to introduce insurance products in light of the need for development of high and new technology industries.</p><p>(...)</p><p>The fund that the State establishes with government funds shall provide discount interest and guaranty to the loans received by enterprises for independent innovation and for application of the achievements in production.</p><p>Policy-oriented financial institutions shall, within the scope of their business, offer special aid to enterprises' projects of independent innovation encouraged by the State.</p><p>(...)</p><p>The State shall encourage the establishment of the fund for guiding investment in pioneering projects to guide the flow of non-government funds towards the enterprises undertaking pioneering projects by way of supporting their development in that direction.</p><p>(...)</p><p>Article 36 The following enterprises shall, in accordance with the relevant regulations of the State, enjoy preferential tax policies: (1) enterprises engaged in research, development and manufacture of high and new technology products;</p><p>(...)</p><p>The relevant departments under the State Council and the people's governments of provinces, autonomous regions and municipalities under the Central Government shall, by adopting such policies as the industrial, financial, energy and environmental protection policies, give guidance to enterprises and urge them to make researches and develop new technologies, products and techniques, to conduct technological transformation and equipment updating, to eliminate outdated equipment and techniques, and to stop manufacturing products with outdated techniques.</p><p>(...)</p><p>Article 60 Government funds for science and technology shall mainly be used for input in the following endeavors: (1) creation of basic conditions and building of facilities for science and technology.</p><p>153. Ainda as peticionárias fizeram referência ao documento Preferential Policies of the National High-tech Industrial Development Zone, que assinala os benefícios concedidos a empresas do setor de alta tecnologia estabelecidas em zonas de desenvolvimento, dentre os quais:</p><p>1. High-tech enterprises levy income tax at a rate of 15%, of which the output value of export products reaches 70% of the total output value of the year, and the income tax is levied at a rate of 10%;</p><p>2. The newly-established high-tech enterprises shall be exempted from income tax within two years from the date of production. The newly established sino-foreign joint venture high-tech enterprises shall be exempted from the profitable year for the first two years from the profit-making year;</p><p>3. The newly-built high-tech enterprises of domestic enterprises shall be exempt from construction tax (or investment direction adjustment tax) for new technology development and production and operation houses;</p><p>4. Instruments and equipment used by high-tech enterprises for high-tech development and high-tech production. Implement rapid depreciation;</p><p>5. With the approval of the Customs, high-tech enterprises can set up bonded warehouses and bonded factories in the high-tech zone;</p><p>6. Export products produced by high-tech enterprises are exempt from export tariffs except those restricted by the state or with specified products;</p><p>7. Infrastructure construction and production and operation capital construction projects in the high-tech industrial development zone. The state arranges a certain amount of capital construction loans and investment scale each year, and can issue a certain amount of long-term bonds to raise funds from the society.</p><p>8. Other preferential policies prescribed by the state.</p><p>According to local actual conditions, local governments have also formulated corresponding preferential policies in taxation, credit, import and export, etc., to promote the development of high-tech industrial development zones in the region.</p><p>154. Esse documento elenca setores presumivelmente inseridos no conceito de alta tecnologia, inclusive:</p><p>(1) Electronics and Information Technology</p><p>1 Computer and external equipment</p><p>2 Microelectronic components</p><p>3 Optoelectronic components</p><p>4 Radio and television technology products</p><p>5 Communication equipment and products</p><p>6 Special process production equipment and test instruments</p><p>155. O Preferential Policies of the National High-tech Industrial Development Zone faz referência a cinco zonas de desenvolvimento: Tianjin, Qingdao, Zhengzhou, Chengdu e Wuhan.</p><p>156. Ainda com relação a zonas de desenvolvimento industrial, cabe ressaltar que várias produtoras de cabos de fibra óptica identificadas estão localizadas em zonas desse tipo, a saber: (i) Jiangsu Zhongtian Technology Co., Ltd. (ZTT) está localizada na Zona de Desenvolvimento Econômico e Tecnológico na cidade de Nantong, Província de Jiangsu; (ii) Jiangsu Zhongli Group Co., Ltd. localizada na Zona de Desenvolvimento Econômico do Sudeste de Changshu na província de Jiangsu; (iii) Changfei Optical Fibre &amp; Cable Co., Ltd. (YOFC) situada na Zona de Desenvolvimento de Alta Tecnologia do Lago Leste da cidade de Wuhan na província de Hubei; (iv) Tianjin Futong Xinmao Technology Co. Ltd. localizada na zona high-tech industrial de Binhai em Tianjin; (v) FiberHomeTelecommunicationTechnologies Co.,Ltd. na Zona High-Tech de Donghu em Wuhan e (vi) Tongding Internet Information Co. situada na Zona de Desenvolvimento Badu na cidade de Zhenze na província de Jiangsu.</p><p>157. Desse modo, é possível correlacionar ações de fomento a zonas de desenvolvimento industrial de alta tecnologia ao setor de cabos de fibra óptica na China.</p><p>158. As peticionárias ressaltaram que, além das medidas estabelecidas para incentivar empresas de cabos de fibra óptica, existem programas relativos às suas matérias-primas. Para tanto, citaram o EU Commission Staff Working Document On Significant Distortions in the Economy of The People's Republic of China for the Purposes of Trade Defence Investigations, que faz referência a (i) incentivos para o desenvolvimento e industrialização de aplicações a jusante de alto valor agregado de novos materiais químicos, incluindo fibras de alto desempenho; (ii) programas nacionais para acelerar o desenvolvimento de produtos estratégicos, incluindo fibras de aramida, largamente utilizadas como reforço de cabos de fibra óptica; e (iii) incentivos para o desenvolvimento de fibras de vidro:</p><p>- Focus on the development of glass-based materials, industrial ceramics, artificial crystals, mineral and organic functional materials, high-performance non-organic fibres and composite materials (p. 285)</p><p>- Similarly, the non-organic non-metal materials such as glass-based materials, industrial ceramics, artificial crystals, high performance fibres and composite materials and graphene and related modified materials are subject to specific development targets. (p. 285)</p><p>- For new chemical materials the Plan aims at supporting the development and industrialisation of high-value added downstream applications such as 'engineering plastics, high performance fibers (...) (p. 420)</p><p>159. No que se refere à política pública chinesa para promover a implantação de rede de banda larga de fibra óptica no país, as peticionárias destacaram o documento governamental Opinions on Promoting the Construction of Optical Fiber Broadband Network, segundo o qual</p><p>"Enterprises that use broadband to develop R&amp;D, technological transformation, and value-added services that meet the requirements of tax laws and regulations can enjoy relevant preferential tax policies in accordance with the law. Include the construction, application, and research and development of optical fiber broadband networks into the encouraged category of the 'Industrial Structure Adjustment Guidance Catalog'. Products and applications based on optical fiber broadband networks that are recognized as national independent innovation products can be included in the 'National Independent Innovation Product Catalog' and 'Government Procurement Independent Innovation Product Catalog'".</p><p>160. O referido documento também estabelece que:</p><p>(...) [l]ocal governments at all levels are encouraged to provide financial subsidies for the use of optical fiber broadband by public service organizations and the construction of high-speed broadband channels in software and service outsourcing parks. Encourage government and industry informatization of optical fiber broadband network applications, promote the popularization of broadband in e-government, medical and health, urban management, community services and other fields, promote broadband-based video applications, and develop broadband-based information services and cultural and creative industries. Continue to use existing funding channels and related policies to encourage college students to start their own businesses based on fiber-optic broadband networks, and support enterprises and units to use fiber-optic broadband networks to develop business and attract college students' employment".</p><p>161. Ainda a partir do documento Opinions on Promoting the Construction of Optical Fiber Broadband Network é possível inferir que além da concessão de tratamento tributário preferencial, existe verdadeiro direcionamento das decisões no setor:</p><p>- In order to implement the "Electronic Information Industry Adjustment and Revitalization Plan", to guide and promote the construction of optical fiber broadband networks, to stimulate the development of domestic related industries, and to give full play to the fundamental and promoting role of optical fiber broadband in national economic and social development, we now propose to promote the construction of optical fiber broadband networks in my country</p><p>- There are still problems such as difficulties in network deployment in communities, unbalanced development in urban and rural areas, and relatively lack of broadband applications. At the same time, telecommunications companies lack enthusiasm due to the large investment and poor efficiency in the construction of optical fiber broadband networks in economically underdeveloped rural areas. The solution of the above-mentioned problems requires relevant policy guidance and support.</p><p>- Telecom companies should carry out fiber-optic broadband network construction in accordance with relevant national regulations and technical specifications, actively adopt multiple modes, demand-oriented, and follow the principle of fiber optics as close to users as possible to accelerate the deployment of fiber optic broadband access networks. Directly deploy optical fiber broadband networks in newly-built areas, and speed up the network transformation of optical fiber in and copper out in established areas. Qualified commercial buildings and parks directly implement fiber-to-the-building and fiber-to-office, and qualified residential quarters directly implement fiber-to-the-building and fiber-to-the-home. Prioritize the use of optical fiber broadband to accelerate the construction of rural information infrastructure and promote optical fiber to the village. Strengthen the co-construction, sharing and effective use of optical fiber broadband networks, and actively promote the integration of the three networks.</p><p>- Competent departments of the communications industry at all levels shall, in conjunction with urban and rural planning, land and resources, and municipal departments, organize telecommunications companies to prepare special plans for transmission lines such as pipelines, poles, and optical cables</p><p>- Accelerate the formulation and improvement of technical standards, engineering specifications, and acceptance specifications related to optical fiber broadband networks, and speed up the introduction and implementation of specifications such as pre-arrangement of optical cables in urban new residential communities and and commercial buildings.</p><p>162. Outro documento de governo citado pelas peticionárias foi o The State Council's issue of the 'Broadband China' strategy and Notification of implementation plan State Development (2013) No. 31, que relaciona incentivos ao desenvolvimento da rede de banda larga na China e destaca:</p>]]></Texto>
  </body>
  <Midias />
</article></xml>